巴蒂塔斯家惨遭灭门
数周之内 斯巴达克斯与逃跑的角斗士震惊卡普亚
一位名叫赛普修斯的年轻贵族派出雇佣军追杀他们
那人肯定挂了
I believe the man dead.
艾力冈
Agron.
找吃的 快点
Supplies. Be quick.
值钱的东西都拿走
Take anything of value.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
你要让他的老二晒太阳
You leave his cock to the sun?
不 我留个信儿
No. I send a message.
给一个老朋友
To an old friend…
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《逃亡》
庞培太傻了 竟然孤军对抗塞托里斯
Pompey was a fool to engage Sertorius absent support.
庞培什么时候考虑过能不能打
When has Pompey ever delayed action in favor of reason?
这么多年了 屠夫小子还是没长大
Advancing in years yet ever the adolescent butcher.
年轻人要经受挫折才能成熟
Where youth plummets, maturity may soar.
如果庞培挡不住叛军
Rome will lose all of Hispania
罗马必然丢掉整个伊伯利亚（西班牙）
if Pompey's numbers are not shored against the renegade.
那么谁能领导这支军队赢得荣誉呢
And who would lead such a force to glorious accolade?
没准是新鲜出炉的民政官吧
Freshly minted praetor, perhaps?
我效忠于共和国 马科斯
I serve the Republic, Marcus.
只要一声令下 我们就为国杀敌
We will take arms against her enemies if so commanded.
民政官的漂亮袍子还没起皱纹呢
The embellished robes of a praetor not yet to wrinkle,
就大谈什么战争和荣誉了
and yet he speaks of war and laurels.
我说的只是国家要务
I speak only of pressing matters.
需要战争和荣誉不用特意出国吧
We need not tread foreign soil to find them,
对吧 瓦里留斯
do we, Varinius?
没错 斯巴达克斯那帮杂种还没落网呢
Not when Spartacus and his mongrels continue to evade capture.
我已经不关心那人的死活了
The man is no longer bound to my concerns.
就在卡普亚城外的道路上
More of young Seppius' men were slaughtered
小赛普修斯死了不少手下
on the road outside Capua.
他说在其中一个死人的身上发现了你的名字
He sends word to me that one of the fallen bore your name,
就刻在那家伙胸前
carved into his chest.
多么悲惨的羁绊
An unfortunate tether.
要快刀斩乱麻
Quickly to be severed.
科萨特斯还在等我
Cossutius awaits my attentions.
代我向令媛道歉
Apologies to your daughter,
我不能留下来一睹芳容了
that I could not linger to gaze upon her.
只要你答应下次来访 我们便能稍感安慰
Disappointment to be tempered with promise of future visit. Hm.
走吧 可以开席了
Come, let us break meal
执政官一个手势
The Consuls will present a motion
就可以派你去卡普亚
dispatching you to Capua at once.
阿比努斯 这种鸡毛蒜皮的小事
This is a simple tumultus, Albinius.
不值得由民政官亲自出马
Undeserving the attentions of a praetor.
是你把色雷斯人带到罗马的 盖尤斯
You brought the Thracian to Roman soil, Gaius.
是你资助了那个笑嘻嘻的巴蒂塔斯
You granted patronage to that grinning shit Batiatus a breath
最后他全家惨遭屠杀
before his house fell to massacre.
我女儿差点就没逃出来
A massacre my daughter barely fucking escaped.
瓦里留斯派人去支援赛普修斯了
Varinius lends his support to Seppius.
如果最后斯巴达克斯落到他手里
If he is the one to bring Spartacus to justice,
那你必定要遭到羞辱
then that victory will be used to embarrass you.
好自为之
Attend to this.
否则你在元老院没有出头之日
Or see yourself rise no further within the Senate.
剑不要放低
Don't lower your sword!
又有八个罗马人
Eight more Romans!
送他们上西天了
Sent to the afterlife!
派拉蒂斯
Peirastes!
给准备好的人换上真家伙
Replace wood with steel, for those who are ready.
维特斯
Vitus!
皮拉斯 莱山德斯
Pyrrhus! Lysandros!
自己挑选趁手的家伙吧
Divide these among you according to skill.
准备好大展身手
And ready the rest for demonstration.
斯巴达克斯 我们需要吃的
Spartacus. We need food.
而不是杀人的家伙
Not more weapons.
他们身上只有武器和钱币
Steel and coin are all they carried.
克雷斯他们好过多了
Crixus' men fare better.
莱斯克斯
Rhaskos.
克雷斯呢
Where is Crixus?
他去找马塞勒斯了 那个拉皮条的
He seeks Marcellus, the cunt peddler.
你们的人收获不错
Your men have done well for themselves.
平均分给大家吧
See everyone to equal portion.
操
Fuck!
你们的东西绰绰有余
You have more than enough.
全是拿命换来的
Gained by blood and risk.
他们除了躺着又出过什么力
What do they do but lay about?
拿出来平分
Divide what you have.
我不说第二遍
I will not ask again.
操蛋的高卢人
Fucking Gauls.
莱斯克斯是个自私的蠢货
Rhaskos is a selfish fool.
眼里只有那点蝇头小利
Unable to see beyond his own desires.
今晚不会有人挨饿
No one will go hungry tonight.
这是最重要的
That is all that matters.
那明天呢
And tomorrow?
明天会死更多罗马人
Will bring death to yet more Romans.
我乐意看到他们全都倒下
I would see all of them struck down.
只要不拿你的命作代价
Yet not at the cost of your life.
我这人注定命大
I have proven troublesome to kill.
没人是你的对手
There is no one that stands your equal.
可对于那些弱者
Yet for those less skilled,
迁徙到东边的山里生活是再好不过了
moving towards the mountains in the east would be sorely welcome.
那里猎物很多
Game is plentiful there.
而且罗马人很少
And Roman numbers sparse.
想法很好
It would be wise.
那我们还等什么
Then why do we stay?
为什么不走呢
What holds us here,
离卡普亚这么近 这么危险
so near Capua and the threat
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
听说你竟敢使唤我的手下
I hear you wish to command my men?
不
No.
只是提醒他们该怎么做
Simply to remind them of what is just.
如果你当时在场 一样会这么做
You would have done the same, had you been present.
我等会跟他们说
I shall have words with them.
由你亲口说 他们更容易接受
They would be better received from your lips.
你又去城里了
You were in town again?
太危险了
You risk discovery.
没人发现 除了马塞勒斯
I was not seen, except by Marcellus.
他永远不会泄露出去
And he will never speak of it.
他的命有用吗
Did his blood bear fruit?
一个名字
A name.
特莱比斯
Trebius.
那个奴隶贩子
The slaver?
跟他有关系吗
He will point towards her?
马塞勒斯说他促成了妮维雅的交易
Marcellus revealed that he brokered deal of Naevia.
我们去哪里找他
Where do we find him?
他每个月都来卡普亚做生意
He frequents Capua upon each moon, to trade his wares.
还去阿米纽斯的窑子找快活
And to wet his cock at Arminius' brothel.
大快人心的消息
News to lift the heart.
我绝不罢手 一定要找回妮维雅
It remains firmly bound, until Naevia is back in my arms.
我在此发誓
I will have those words now.
克雷斯
Crixus?
你有没有见到教练
Have you had sight of Doctore?
训练场是他的命根子
The ludus was his life's blood.
要是让他看到血溅训练场的人
To lay eyes upon those who have spilled it…
无异于伤口上撒盐
It would salt mortal wound.
你简直像个娘们 快他妈的动手
You fight like a woman! Fucking kill him!
难看死了
A poor showing.
抱歉 行政官
Apologies, Magistrate.
他们已经是优中选优了
These were the best that could be procured.
观众们喜欢大场面 蒙卡图
The crowd demands spectacle, Mercato.
要分散他们的注意力 避免城市陷入混乱
They must be distracted, lest the city fall to ill temper and panic.
还看什么角斗比赛
Gladiators and games.
斯巴达克斯和他的杀人团伙还在逃呢
While Spartacus and his murdering horde roam free.
你哥哥正在积极处理这件事 赛皮娅
Your brother has the matter well in hand, Seppia.
这话挺安慰人的
Words of comfort.
对于他今早损失的八个手下来说
To the eight of his men slaughtered this morning.
八个
Eight?
抱歉
Apologies.
有急事耽误了…
Pressing business conspired to delay me
真的吗 赛普修斯
Is it true, Seppius?
又有八个人死在斯巴达克斯手里吗
Eight more of your men, fallen to Spartacus?
小事一桩
A thing of little note.
斯巴达克斯很快就会举手投降了
Spartacus will soon be brought to terms.
然后为我们亲爱的堂兄赛克斯报仇
And our beloved cousin Sextus avenged.
或者你难逃一劫
Or you to join him,
留我一个人无依无靠
leaving me woefully unattended.
我是这么无情的哥哥吗
What form of brother would I be,
连最亲爱的妹妹也不要了
to abandon such cherished blood?
难看死了
A poor showing.
我身上没钱
I have nothing of worth.
我们只要答案
We seek only words.
这个我也没有
I am absent them as well.
你是巴蒂塔斯家的人吧
You were Batiatus' man, were you not?
你认错人了
You are mistaken.
他名叫奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus, he was called.
你很幸运不是那家伙
It is fortunate you are not him.
他犯有背叛主人的重罪
The man stands accused of turning upon his dominus.
捉拿他的赏金相当可观
The reward for his capture is a substantial sum.
斯巴达克斯就更贵了
Towards Spartacus yet higher.
如果他被抓了
If he were to be revealed,
你这样的人就可以逍遥自在了
a man such as you could continue not being himself.
我说过 我身上没钱
As I said, I have nothing of worth.
但有赏金
A lesser sum then.
抱歉
Apologies.
你不是巴蒂塔斯家的人
You are not Batiatus' man.
你不该出来
You should not be outside.
我想看看月亮
I wanted to see the moon.
雅努斯喜欢看月亮
Janus loves to gaze upon it.
维罗把他举过肩膀
Varro would hoist him upon his shoulders
他会伸出双手
and he would stretch his hands out,
想要把月亮从空中摘下来
attempting to wrest it from the heavens.
也许有一天他能做到
Perhaps one day he shall.
但不会踩在他父亲的肩膀上
But not upon his father's shoulders.
雅努斯太小了 还不太记事
Janus is yet too young for memory to take proper hold.
也许他长大后会忘了我今天的样子
I doubt he would recall the sight of me now.
你是他的母亲
You are his mother.
岁月也不能改变这一点
Years would not lessen such a bond.
他会在你的注视下成长 犹如东升的旭日
He will burst as sun through clouds, at the sight of you.
自从我们分开 我就梦想着这样的场景
I have dreamt of nothing else since our parting.
米拉常常说起东边的大山
Mira speaks of the mountains, to the east.
我在考虑是不是派人去那里打猎
I have thoughts dispatching men to hunt for game.
你哥哥照顾雅努斯 他离那儿不远 对吧
Your brother tends to Janus not far from there, does he not?
月亮伸手可及
The moon within closer reach.
我可以缩短你们的距离
I would shorten the distance.
你以为我不希望这样吗
You think I have not longed to have it so?
远远地离开你们
To be far from all of this?
我和你们一样打上了逃犯的烙印
I am branded fugitivus with the rest of you.
这种朝不保夕的生活 我又怎么照顾儿子呢
What life could I offer my son beneath such shadow?
没错
None.
只有离开罗马才行
Within the Republic.
这是从我们上路到现在积攒的钱币
All the coin I have relieved the Romans of since our escape.
足够作你和儿子的盘缠了
Enough to buy you and your son passage,
- 远走高飞吧 - 斯巴达克斯
- far from these shores. - Spartacus…
维罗临终时就提到你和雅努斯
Varro's last words were of you and Janus.
要我好好照顾你们
That I see you cared for.
不用说我也要做到
They need not have been spoken.
给克里斯坎蒂亚带话
Send word to Crescentia that
我们这周的午餐时间都要推迟
I must move our mid-day meals later in the week.
还有回应瓦鲁斯的请求
And respond to Varus' request
就说我们出席他的庆典
for our presence at his celebration.
我们不出席
We will not be attending.
我知道你不喜欢那家伙
I know you do not care for the man,
不过他人脉很广
yet he is well connected.
我们必须出席
We must make appearance.
这都要怪你父亲
It's your father would have it otherwise.
他派我去卡普亚
He dispatches me to Capua.
处理斯巴达克斯的事
To deal with Spartacus.
我再找他谈谈
I will have word with him.
他决心已定
He is set upon it.
你是民政官 盖尤斯
You are a praetor, Gaius.
追杀奴隶的事情太下作了
Hunting errant slaves is beneath you.
可是非做不可
Yet it must be done.
不过我答应你 在孩子降生前
But I promise we will return to Roman well
我们肯定能回到罗马
before our child enters this world.
我们
We?
你当然要陪我去
You will accompany me of course.
我不去
I will not.
出去
Out.
我因为资助的事情结交了巴蒂塔斯家
I am bound to the House of Batiatus by patronage.
结果呢 你犯下人命案 要我擦屁股
Granted only to bury knowledge of the blood staining your hands.
莱姬尼娅的事完全是意外
What happened to Licinia was an accident.
她是马科斯•克拉苏的堂妹
She was cousin of Marcus Crassus!
她是个臭婊子
She was a fucking bitch!
所有知道真相的人
All who knew of the deed
都不在了
speak no more.
别想这件事了
Let us put it behind us.
想得美
I intend to.
去准备吧
Now make preparations.
我们去卡普亚
We leave for Capua.
了结与斯巴达克斯的恩怨
And an end to the curse of Spartacus.
你居然相信马塞勒斯的话
You believe the words of Marcellus,
刀搁在脖子上逼出来的话
bleated from tongue with sword to neck?
克雷斯要去阿米纽斯的窑子了
Crixus moves on Arminius and his place of whores.
我要助他一臂之力
and I will be at his side.
现在高卢人当老大了吗
So we follow the fucking Gaul now?
我发过誓要帮忙
I swore aid in the matter.
你们没有
You did not.
如果你们不管 我不会有想法
I would not think less, if you stayed from it.
我跟你去
I am with you.
我喜欢窑子
You had me at whores.
不要冒无谓的险
Avoid unnecessary risk,
不要乱说话调戏克雷斯
and provoking words towards the Gauls.
派拉蒂斯负责打猎
Peirastes leads the hunt for game.
他会一路保护你找到儿子
He will have you safely to your son's arms.
回到你离开太久的家园
From where you have been too long absent.
把儿子抚养成人
See your boy to a man.
也许有一天 我能与他兄弟相称
That I may one day greet him as a brother.
我会给雅努斯讲你的事
I will tell Janus of you.
告诉他 你对他父亲的爱无人可比
Of the man who loved his father above all others.
她走了吗
She takes to foot?
还债
Long overdue.
今晚还有很多债要还
As are many things this night.
你不用去拼命 斯巴达克斯
This is not your fight, Spartacus.
我发过誓 以鲜血和荣耀之名
I gave my word. Blood and honor.
说到做到
It yet speaks to the man.
那就用罗马人的惨叫撕开沉沉的夜幕吧
Then let us split darkness with the cries of Romans.
快去
Go!
特莱比斯
Trebius!
特莱比斯在哪里
Where is Trebius?
在哪里
Where!
- 给我滚起来 - 不
- Get off the fucking floor! - No!
给我滚起来 臭婊子
Get off the fucking floor! Bitch!
特莱比斯
Trebius.
我有话问你
I would have words.
我没有
I would not.
不
No!
就是他
Your man?
很多卫兵 我们必须…
More guards! We need
- 特莱比斯 该死的混蛋 - 艾力冈
- Trebius. You fucking cunt! - Agron
就是这个罗马畜生把我和杜罗卖给巴蒂塔斯
This is the Roman shit that sold me and Duro to Batiatus.
要不是他 我兄弟就不会死
My brother would be alive if it were not for him!
他知道妮维雅的下落
He knows the whereabouts of Naevia.
我们要带他走
We will take him and go.
他坚持不了多久
He will not last.
我需要时间
I need but a moment.
我们帮你争取
Then you shall have it.
这家伙快死了
The man meets his end.
这不就行了吗
That is all that matters.
你促成了巴蒂塔斯家那个女人的买卖
You brokered the sale of a woman from the House of Batiatus.
黑皮肤
Dark of skin,
肩膀后面有主人家的标记
the mark of the domina upon the back of her shoulder.
她在哪里
Where is she?
滚去吃屎
Fuck yourself.
我已经死了
I am already dead.
你还有一口气
There is yet life in you yet.
说出来 我给你一个痛快
Speak, and see it ended quickly.
南边
South?
那里有宅子和农场 离城市很远
There are villas and farms, far from the city.
妮维雅就在其中一家吗
And Naevia was sold to one of them?
不 她被转手多次
No. She was handed from dominus to dominus.
巴蒂塔斯为了当市政官 把她当礼物铺路
A gift from Batiatus, to secure favor on his campaign for fucking Aedile.
你说的地方
These places you speak of.
防御有多严密
How heavily are they guarded?
只要老天爷有眼 多严密都无所谓
It would not matter if the gods stood watch.
南边有多少宅子
How many villas are there in the south?
距离相隔多远
Over what spread of distance?
你怎么知道妮维雅曾经到过那里
How will you know if Naevia's even located in one of them?
只有几家宅子属于贵族
Only a few are owned by men of note.
巴蒂塔斯舔的肯定是他们的屁股
Cocks Batiatus would have sucked to further his cause.
光天化日之下行动
To be exposed, in the open.
我们必须谨慎行事
We must proceed with caution.
你还好意思说谨慎
You? Advising caution?
真是乌鸦笑猪黑
The tempest shouts for the breeze to calm itself.
你死了对妮维雅有何好处
What good will your death be to Naevia,
我们必须计划好再行动
if we do not pause to think?
她已经离开我太久了
She has been from my arms too long.
我没时间坐下来思考
I do not have time to sit and ponder.
我们都没时间
None of us do now.
你什么意思
What is your meaning?
特莱比斯临死前提到了罗马人
With his last breath, Trebius frothed of Roman,
死神已经从那里启程
and the death that has been dispatched from her bosom,
要置我们于死地
to wash us away in rivers of blood.
是罗马军队吗
Soldiers?
天亮就到
Arriving with the sun.
谁指挥
Who leads them?
整座城市都陷入恐慌
The city is in a panic.
阿米纽斯那边遭到突袭 死了很多人
Scores were slaughtered in the raid against Arminius.
停
Halt!
带他们吃饭休息
See the men fed and rested.
日落前分组搜索郊外
Squads to sweep the countryside by nightfall.
遵命 长官
Your will, Praetor.
解散
Fall out.
卸粮
Bring supplies.
您带足了人马吗
Do you have enough men for this?
看起来您的手下并不多
It does not appear you have enough men.
对付奴隶而已
They face only slaves.
又不是大军压境的汉尼拔
Not Hannibal at the gates.
他们都是角斗士
They are gladiators.
为首的是屠影英雄斯巴达克斯…
Led by Spartacus, the Slayer of the Shadow of the
行政官呢
Where is the Magistrate?
我要跟有身份的人讨论此事
I would discuss this with someone of note.
他在别处耽搁了 鉴于昨晚的情形
He is otherwise detained, in view of last night's
他表示歉意
He sends apologies.
不过赛普修斯非常希望有人找他谈
Seppius however is eager for audience.
那家伙是民政官瓦里留斯的耳目
The man has Praetor Varinius' ear.
再说我也不需要听他嚼舌根
I have no desire for his tongue to fill mine as well.
我要公开讲话 安抚民众的情绪
I would address the people, put their minds to ease.
明天日出时分 就安排在市集里
Tomorrow as the sun rises in the marketplace.
您打算说什么
What will you say?
只管安排
Attend to the arrangements.
是 长官
Yes, Praetor.
为什么带我来这里
Why have I been brought here?
盖尤斯 为什么带我来这里
Gaius, why have I been brought here?
来他们家
To this House?
山顶的视野非常好 便于观察四周
The hilltop offers excellent vantage of the surrounding country.
底下的训练场方便驻扎军队
The ludus below will easily garrison my men.
那就好好利用吧
Then use it as such.
我要回到父亲的宅邸
I will remove myself to my father's villa.
你就留在我身边
You will stay at my side.
现在去把房间打点好
Now, set the house to order.
现在这里是我们的家了 伊莉西娅
This is our home now, Ilithyia.
直到斯巴达克斯完蛋
Until Spartacus falls.
这里所有的东西全他妈的丢到悬崖下面
I want everything in this fucking house seen over the cliff.
全都换成新的 不管出多少钱
We will purchase a new appointment much coin.
如果我的夫君要我留在这里
If my husband would have me here,
他肯定愿意出这个钱
he can certainly pay for the comfort.
把所有的血迹都弄干净
And see all traces of blood cleansed.
到处都是巴蒂塔斯和黄脸婆的臭味
It reeks of Batiatus and his faded bitch.
- 去呀 - 是 女主人
- Go! Go! - Yes, Domina.
出什么事了
What has happened?
我妻子闹出来的事
In matters concerning my wife,
诸神都想不出来
the gods themselves fear to speculate.
你疯了吗
Have you lost wit?
说话
Speak.
你们来之前应该通知一声
You should have sent word you were coming…
我们好准备宴会
We would have prepared a feast.
露迪雅
Lucretia.
你看见了 看见了
You see it then? You see it?
妮维雅 给贵客倒酒
Naevia! Bring wine for our honored guests.
- 杀了她 杀她 杀啊 - 长官
- Kill it. Kill it, KILL IT! - Praetor!
她是巴蒂塔斯的妻子吗
This is Batiatus' wife?
模样相似的幽灵罢了
A shadow of the same.
那她还活着
And yet she lives.
能在大屠杀中幸存…
To be spared from such carnage…
这是诸神的祝福
A blessing from the gods.
如果传播出去 能起到安抚人心的效果
One that would calm a city, if it were known to be such.
妮维雅
Naevia!
抱歉
Apologies.
我不知道她去哪儿了
I do not know where she's gone.
你为什么不动手
Why do you pause?
她可以提供有力的证明
She could prove a powerful symbol.
人们看到这个女人
It would give the city hope,
从斯巴达克斯等人手下生还 就能重获希望
to see a woman survive Spartacus and his men.
就能鼓起勇气
And courage to confront them,
您也能尽快回到罗马
speeding your return to Rome.
盖尤斯
Gaius.
你不能留她活着
You cannot let her live.
带她洗澡 好好照顾
See her bathed and tended.
不要刺激她的神经
And what fragments her shattered mind yet holds.
罗马军队
The Roman army?!
我们死定了
We are all of us dead!
少他妈胡扯
Grab your fucking cock!
这不是我们想要的
We never wanted this.
你们这些角斗士要害死我们
You gladiators, you will see us all to our end!
小混蛋
You little fuck!
艾力冈
Agron!
我们早知道有这一天
We knew this day would come.
有人担心这一天的到来
Some have feared its approach.
有人则很渴望
Others have longed for it.
还有人早就明白其中深意
Yet few have grasped deeper meaning.
这一刻
That this moment,
注定要面对
was always fated to be so.
我发过誓
I made promise.
向你们发过誓 就在巴蒂塔斯家灭亡当天
To all of you, when the House of Batiatus fell.
我们要让罗马发抖
That we would see Rome tremble.
现在该发抖的是你们
You are the ones that shall quake.
我亲眼看到葛雷博带手下进城了
I have witnessed Glaber and his men entering the city.
人数众多
Enough in number
来取你们的命
to end your lives.
跟我们一起 加大我们的筹码
Then stand with us, and balance the odds.
蒙卡图说葛雷博将在市集发表演讲
Mercato has announced Glaber will make address
就在明天一早
in the market as day breaks.
到时候没人注意你们
It would be wise to use the distraction,
不要妄想对抗了
and leave such thoughts behind.
教练
Doctore…
我已经不是教练了
That is no longer my title.
你要去哪儿
Where do you go?
只有一个地方可去
There is but one place.
对于失去荣誉的野兽来说
For an animal without honor.
我们失去他了
He is lost to us.
还有多少人跟着你
How many more would you have follow?
跟我们一起 兄弟
Join with us, brother.
我们往南走 趁着葛雷博发表演讲
We can head south, while Glaber cups his balls and makes speeches.
我就是为了等他才留下来
He's the reason I am here.
我妻子永远回不来了
And my wife forever absent.
你时常告诫我要谨慎
You often preach to me about caution.
现在轮到你来听劝了
Turn advice now towards self.
我们准备好了
We are ready.
打杂的奴隶也能跟军队拼命
House slaves, playing at being men?
他们不是角斗士
They are not gladiators.
你手里没有军队 不管你有多么渴望
They are not an army, as much you wish it to be so.
再说吧 斯巴达克斯
Sleep upon it, Spartacus.
等到明天日出 希望你能想清楚
But when the sun rises, I would see reason dawn.
水
Water.
哪儿来的水 现在可是旱季
How did we come by it, with the drought?
旱季早过了
The drought is long past.
你不记得旱季结束了吗
Do you not recall its ending?
没关系
It is of no concern.
来 我帮你擦干 然后换衣服
Come, I would have you dry and seen to proper dress.
你的伤
Your wound.
伤
Wound?
怎么弄的
How did you come by it?
退下
Leave us.
肯定非常恐怖
It must have been terrible.
困在这里逃不出去
Trapped within these walls…
家养的野兽疯狂嗜血
Your beasts running wild…
所有人都以为你死了
Everyone believed you dead,
跌下悬崖
smashed upon the cliffs…
摔得粉身碎骨
Bits of bone and flesh
什么都不剩
your only testament.
你是怎么一个人活下来
How did you survive, all alone?
露迪雅
Lucretia…
我们是朋友 对吧
We are friends. Are we not?
亲密无间
The very best.
你还有很多朋友
And you have so many.
艾美莉娅
Aemilia.
凯西莉娅
Caecilia.
莱姬尼娅
Licinia.
马科斯•克拉苏的堂妹
Cousin to Marcus Crassus…
如果能认识她可就太荣幸了
It would be a very great honor to be seen at her side.
你能为我引见吗
Would you make introduction?
我们去换衣服
Let us see you dressed.
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia.
你为什么不告诉我
Why didn't you tell me?
你怀孕了
You are with child!
昆图斯跟我努力了很久
Quintus and I have been trying for such a long time.
这是预兆
This is a sign.
诸神的预兆
A sign from the gods.
巴蒂塔斯家必将人丁兴旺
Life blossoms in the House of Batiatus…
这就是我们留在卡普亚的原因
This is why we are yet in Capua.
送走奥瑞莉娅的原因
Why you saw Aurelia away.
你希望他们派葛雷博来
You hoped they would send Glaber.
不
No.
我祈祷如此
I prayed for it.
你现在又祈祷什么呢
And what do you pray for now?
对着你并不信仰的诸神
To the Gods you do not believe in?
你妻子希望这样吗
Would your wife have wanted this?
看着夫君送死
To see her husband consumed?
她不希望的事情太多了
There are many things she would not have wanted.
结果都成真了
And yet they are so.
跟着克雷斯往南走
Follow Crixus to the south.
别让复仇的火焰葬送那些你辛苦救下的人
Do not let your vengeance claim so many you have saved from bondage.
我不会再让一个人因我而死
I would not see another life forfeit to my desires.
我们会找到妮维雅
We will find Naevia.
远离罗马的爪牙
And move far beyond grasp of Rome.
远离你所背负的这个名字 斯巴达克斯
Far from the name Spartacus they have branded you with.
与其思考飘渺不定的将来
Let us turn thought from uncertain future.
不如抓住每分每秒…
And embrace fleeting moment…
起来
Get up!
全他妈的站好
Move to fucking purpose.
准备接受命令
Be ready when word is given.
你这口气就像主人
You bark as a dominus.
面对血盆大口 绵羊才知道跑
Sheep stand idle, if not prodded by snapping jaw.
起来
Get up!!
小狗的嘴巴也有这种效果吗
Does the maw of a pup spur the same?
那咱们对咬吧 马上知道答案
Let us compare teeth, and have answer.
别吵了
Cease your quarrels.
我来找斯巴达克斯 听他的想法
I am for Spartacus, and the lay of his thoughts.
昨晚他知道要谨慎行事了
Last night they were towards heeding caution,
决定跟你们去南边
and joining you in the south.
到了早上呢
And the light of morning?
早上我醒的时候他已经走了
He was gone from our bed when I awoke.
没有必要这么担心
There is no cause for rising concerns!
城里的局势已经得到控制
The situation is well in control!
阿米纽斯那事儿呢
What of Arminius?!
这他妈的也叫控制住了
Is that fucking control?!
当然不
No.
那是野蛮人的行为
It was an act of savagery,
是只懂杀戮的野兽所为
committed by animals who know nothing more.
也是这群野兽制造了巴蒂塔斯家血案
These same beasts laid waste to the House of Batiatus.
那晚死了很多人
Many were lost that night.
体面的女人
Women of proper standing.
有身份地位的男人
Men of honor and position.
我的堂兄赛克斯
My own cousin Sextus,
多年备受爱戴的行政官
your beloved Magistrate of years past,
也没逃过一劫
among the dead.
他说的对
He speaks the truth!
全都死于疯狂嗜血杀戮的屠夫之手
At the hands of butchers, who crave only blood and death.
他们也将付出同样的代价
And they shall see it returned in kind.
但是他们由斯巴达克斯带领
But Spartacus leads them!
瑟奥科斯也不是他的对手
Even Theokoles fell before him!
他是携雨之使者
He's the bringer of rain!
斯巴达克斯区区凡人一个
Spartacus is but a man!
并不是所有人都死在他手里
And not all fall to his touch.
昆图斯•兰图拉斯•巴蒂塔斯的妻子
The wife of Quintus Lentulus Batiatus
经受了斯巴达克斯及其走狗的残忍屠杀
stood against the merciless assault of Spartacus and his dogs!
诸神怜悯
And by favor of the gods…
她还活着
she yet lives!
真是奇迹
It's a miracle!
赞美诸神
Gods be praised!
这是赐福
It is a blessing!
你黯然失色了
You stand eclipsed.
她就是预兆
She is their herald,
是从往生世界归来传递信息的人
plucked from the shores of the afterlife to deliver a message!
斯巴达克斯绝对无法
That Spartacus shall never triumph
征服卡普亚的人民
over the people of Capua!
他来了
He comes…
he comes…
他来了
保持镇定
Still yourself.
诸神还给了我们另一个征兆
And yet the gods grace us with further signs
斯巴达克斯的末日近了
that Spartacus' end is near!
杀了她
Get rid of her!
剁了这婊子
Gut the cunt!
我手下遭遇了几个巴蒂塔斯家的奴隶
My men came upon a clutch of Batiatus' slaves,
他们打算前往东边山里作恶
attempting harm in the mountains to the east.
只有这个贱货活了下来
This one is all that remains among the living.
在她因伤而死之前
Before she succumbs to her wounds,
我要逼她坦白
I will force her tongue to purpose.
在她临死前
And with her dying breath,
她就会说出斯巴达克斯及其走狗的下落
she will tell me where Spartacus and his men hide themselves.
然后就将他们
And they shall be struck,
斩草除根
from this mortal world
由我盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博动手
by the hand Gaius Claudius Glaber!
得意的小杂种
Preening little shit.
我很喜欢他
I rather favor him.
谢谢
Thank you.
围住他
Surround him!
干掉他
Cease him!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
干掉他
Cease him!
带奥瑞莉娅走
Take Aurelia and go!
拿下他
Take him!
你赢不了的
You cannot win this!
不
No!
留下来 就永远别指望报仇了
Stay, and see vengeance forever denied.
你不比莱斯克斯和该死的高卢人强
You are no better than Rhaskos and the fucking Gauls.
满脑子都是报私仇
All driven only by your own desires.
我们对你都不重要吗
Do any of us hold fucking worth to you?
所以我一个人去
The reason I went alone.
还顶嘴 如果你落到葛雷博手里呢
A hard comfort, if you had fallen to Glaber's men.
艾力冈会带着你们往南走
Agron would have led you south.
我们需要领袖
We need a leader.
而不是一个愣头青
Not some angry boy who can barely piss
动不动就到处撒气
without splashing everyone about him.
你想要我怎么做
What would you have me do?
放过那个奴役我妻子的人
Turn from the man that condemned my wife to slavery?
饶他性命
Let him live,
他夺走了我的一切
that took everything from me?
你的心还在跳动
Your heart still beats.
你靠近听听
Place ear to chest,
你就能发现它早已死了
and you will find it absent sound.
但你还活着
And yet you are not dead.
因为你
Because of you.
我很感激你
Know that you have my gratitude
我不是去帮你的 你这个疯子
I didn't come to lend you aid, you mad fuck.
我是去阻止你
I came to stop you.
你要拦着我不去找葛雷博复仇吗
You would place yourself between Glaber and what he deserves?
正如你拦着我不去找妮维雅
As you would place yourself between Naevia and me.
你以为杀死一个民政官
What do you think would be the result
会有什么样的后果
of killing a fucking praetor?
元老院绝对大发雷霆
The Senate would burn upon itself,
气势汹汹地来寻仇
belching forth fire and vengeance.
他们绝不会像葛雷博那样只带一队士兵
They would not send a few men, as they do with Glaber.
他们会派出成千上万人
They would send thousands.
真正的军队
A true army.
而我们根本不是
Which we will never be.
奥瑞莉娅找你
Aurelia calls for you.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus…
我来了
I am here.
答应…我…
Promise… me…
任何事
Anything.
答应我 你不会碰我儿子
Promise… you will stay far from my son.
我不要他死在你的面前
I would not have him die in your wake…
跟他的父母一样
as his father and mother…
葛雷博和他的走狗要血债血偿
Glaber and his men will pay in blood.
去拿剑
Gather swords
不
No.
我们往南走
We move south.
去找妮维雅
To find Naevia.
让克雷斯带他的高卢人寻梦去吧
Let Crixus and the other Gauls chase lost hope.
- 斯巴达克斯 - 我意已决
- Spartacus - The decision's been made.
我们必须团结
We must stand as one.
分裂必亡
Or fall divided.
这是残酷的教训
A lesson hard learned.
我们所经之地 所有的奴隶都将获得解放
Shackle will be struck from every slave upon our path.
我们要壮大队伍
We will see our numbers grow.
当我们拥有一支军团
And when they have become legion,
再去面对葛雷博
we will face Glaber,
还有罗马的军队
and the hordes of Rome again.
诸神将会为他们的遭遇伤心哭泣
And the gods shall weep for their suffering.